<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.1" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Winter 1873-1874</title>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>The man had been covertly watching Van der Boschstraat 12 for
    several days waiting for a chance to catch Johan Jacob alone but the
    overbearing woman of the house had shown no inclination to go out. Johan
    Jacob could be seen in his workroom, presumably pouring over his maps upon
    the hour rather than venturing beyond his front door. It was, of course,
    only a matter of time before he answered the call of the ladies available
    to cater to his less cerebral needs. IIt was a pity that such a sojourn
    would take place in the chill of a winter evening which fact meant that
    the man had to suffer the wind, rain, sleet, and general inclemency of the
    season with only the slight benefit of the cover of darkness. His feet
    were numb with cold but the option of stamping some life back into them
    was not open to him as it might give away his presence to some nosey
    busybody. His chilblains burnt and itched, his reddened nose seemed always
    decorated with a terminating drip and he was in desperate need of
    something to warm his internal organs, preferably not soup.</para>

    <para>Now the weather had cleared up to reveal an almost full moon and
    brilliant with stars. Very nice and all that but the increased
    illumination made remaining invisible more difficult added to which the
    temperature was plummeting towards a hard frost. Ah, but look here! The
    front door was opening and, yes, the familiar figure of his quarry was
    emerging from it! The man quietly slipped onto the pavement behind Johan
    Jacob and followed him to a distance safely out of view from the house
    before he took a small, round stone from his pocket and lobbed it at Johan
    Jacob's shoulder. Without breaking his stride, Johan Jacob walked on then
    suddenly diverged from his route and stopped in the concealing shelter of
    a low hanging tree. The man walked past, looking and listening, before
    satisfying himself that they were alone and turning back to also duck
    under the willow branches where Johan Jacob was waiting
    expectantly.</para>

    <para>"Your taking ship for Sumatra, first tide, day after tomorrow. Go in
    uniform but take informal tropical clothing. We will sort you out some
    scruffy stuff when you get there. Travel light and go armed. You'll be
    away months rather than weeks. Questions? "</para>

    <para> Johan Jacob stared thoughtfully at his shoes then nodded his head
    to accept the brief before adding,</para>

    <para>"Then I had better make haste and make full use of the delights at
    my destination."</para>

    <para>With that, he turned on his heel and strode off into the
    night.</para>

    <para>The man waited until the footsteps had died away before peering
    through the drooping willow branches to ensure that the coast was He
    quietly took himself off in the direction of the less salubrious parts of
    Den Haag where he would not attract attention in a smoke-filled bar which
    specialised in cheap jenever. The result of his efforts to defrost by the
    ingestion of rough spirit was that pretty much all of him had gone numb by
    the time he left for the docks at Scheveningen. Luckily the imastless,
    ronclad monitor vessel he was to rendezvous with was easily spotted
    amongst the sailing ships and steam-sailers in port. The
    <emphasis>Heiligerlee</emphasis> was a common sight along the coast of
    Holland so attracted no undue interest by arriving in Sceveningen.</para>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Then Theodrus and Cornelis shut themselves up in the makeshift
    office and let it be known that they were only to be disturbed in case of
    dire emergency. Any knocks on the door or timid calls were ignored. Their
    agreed strategy was to take an imaginary walk through the house, compiling
    lists of unfinished work in each room as they went. They also had a draft
    of the celebrations planned for the day of Marcellus's 50th anniversary as
    <emphasis>Burgermeester </emphasis>.</para>

    <para>The obvious place to start was at the <emphasis>ingang</emphasis>,
    or entrance, and the vestibule beyond it. Placed in the centre of the the
    seven bays on the ground floor, the large, sturdy wooden door was already
    in place. Although it opened as a single door, a central column decorated
    with vines and grapes gave the impression of double doors. Symmetrical
    panels were glazed and decorated with wrought ironwork. Above and below
    each inset glass were carved panels, oblong below and circular bosses
    topped with semi-circular arches above. The rich colour of the wood and
    the multi-faceted carvings were pleasing to the eye and the whole was
    clearly designed to signal the protection it offered to the valuable
    contents which would eventually be contained within. Cornelis was proud of
    the skill he had exhibited in creating it and Theodorus thought this was
    rightly so.</para>

    <para>But, they couldn't linger in admiration as there was a long way to
    go and both agreed that the impressive entry needed no improvement. Once
    inside, an entrance hall led up to the doorway into the
    <emphasis>gang</emphasis>, or inner hall, marking the transition from the
    public areas of the house to the family's private quarters. The public
    rooms were reached through doors leading off either side of the vestibule,
    one to a small salon on the left and one to a reception area on the right.
    In order to create the impression of symmetry, two false doors opposite
    the real ones, had been created with a central bay of plasterwork between
    them. Since this was the first impression visitors, not to mention
    Marcellus, would have it needed to show how important and wealthy the
    occupants of the house were. The decoration of the vestibule was,
    therefore, designed to provide an opulent impression but as a backdrop for
    the displays of valuable items and family crests destined to be placed
    there. So, whilst the ceiling rose, cornicing and the headers above the
    doors involved complex plaster mouldings which had been delicately painted
    in muted creams, the central panels were relatively plain with a touch of
    blue in places to set off the blue of the Chinese plates destined to be
    hung nearby. A marble floor provided the finishing touch to this
    relatively small but hugely important space.</para>

    <para>The first room off the vestibule was the
    <emphasis>spreekkamer,</emphasis> or reception room. This would be where
    the maid who answered the door would take visitors to wait whilst she
    conveyed messages to and from the occupants of the house. Tradespeople
    would wait here to be paid and more important callers be divested of their
    outerwear before being admitted to the <emphasis>grote salon</emphasis>
    through the far door. A relatively plain room, then. Even so, it was yet
    to be finished as the expensive red flock wallpaper from England, chosen
    as a foil for the gilt framed paintings destined to be displayed against
    it, remained to be hung. Again, concerns about keeping the decoration
    clean came to the surface as flock wallpaper was notorious for attracting
    dirt. Since the guests admitted to the house for Marcellus's celebration
    were by invitation only, it was agreed that the completion of this room
    could be assigned a low priority and it was sealed off.</para>

    <para>The same could not be said of the <emphasis>kleine salon</emphasis>
    through the left hand door off the vestibule. This was where Marcellus
    planned greet important political and business visitors and provide them
    with refreshments. An opportunity to make an impression which was too good
    to pass up so a suite of fashionable, expensive furnishings had been
    commissioned from Horrix of Den Haag, who made furniture for the King's
    house. Unlike the light, bright vestibule, the palette of the
    <emphasis>kleine salon </emphasis>darkened to for the ornate fireplace in
    black and cocoa brown for the walls. Deep creams and gold decorating the
    ceiling with its complex cornicing and fine ceiling rose from which a huge
    crystal chandelier was destined to cascade and glitter with candlelight
    or, on a good day, sunlight through the single window. Without the
    glittering chandelier and rich red of the upholstery and carpet, the room
    Theodorus and Cornelis were considering would have seemed dull were it not
    for the opulence of the plasterwork with its detail picked out in gold.
    Theodorus had minutely inspected these mouldings and was pleased with
    their execution. Another room they could agree was as finished as they
    could make it.</para>

    <para>There were two doors off the <emphasis>kleine salon</emphasis>, one
    to the <emphasis>kantor</emphasis>, or office, at the front of the house
    and the other through into the <emphasis>gang</emphasis>. The latter was
    envisaged as to be used only by family and their servants and was now
    sealed off on the <emphasis>gang</emphasis> side. As was the doorway at
    the end of the vestibule. Now that all the work in the rooms at the front
    of the house which were to be used for the celebration had been done, the
    challenge was to keep it in pristine condition despite the mess being
    created by work in progress in the rest of the house. The opening out of
    the vestibule had been built to double thickness to accommodate two doors,
    one after the other, to symbolise its gate-keeping importance. To create a
    further barrier, provision had been made for a heavy curtain to span the
    width of the wall at the end of the vestibule thus concealing the entry to
    the domestic area beyond. For now, a temporary curtain had been hung here
    then both doors closed with the door on the family side sealed to shield
    the completed rooms from the dust and grime beyond. Use of the front door
    had been banned with everything and everyone coming and going through
    either the kitchen or garden room entrances.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Now the difficulties for Theodorus and Cornelis started. The
    <emphasis>gang</emphasis> was the hub of the house so still constantly in
    use by men working on the upstairs rooms yet time needed to be devoted to
    getting it ready for the grand event in August. This meant that all of the
    upstairs rooms which would be needed had to be given priority now so that
    they, too, could be sealed off whilst the central
    <emphasis>gang</emphasis> , <emphasis>trappenhuis</emphasis>, or
    staircase, and <emphasis>witte overloop</emphasis>, or white landing, were
    decorated. Then, working forwards, the ground floor family rooms must be
    completed, not to mention laying the groundwork for a working kitchen. All
    of this must be made ready in time for carpets to be laid, curtains hung,
    furniture placed, and all the many objects put on display. The only slight
    relief to this immense schedule of work was the decision by the family not
    to use part of the house. Paulina and her husband would be returning to
    their own house to sleep so the upstairs suite of rooms behind the
    carefully installed<emphasis> witte bovenportaal</emphasis>, or white
    screen and door, would not be needed. Also, since Marcellus was not the
    host but the guest of honour, the formal <emphasis>grote salon</emphasis>
    and <emphasis>eetkamer, </emphasis>or dining room, intended as function
    rooms would not be needed either. Already these rooms had been tidied and
    cleaned with the workmen redeployed to other parts of the house.</para>

    <para>The situation which had been the trigger for the heated exchange
    between Theodorus and Cornelis earlier in the day now had to be addressed.
    The area of the house into which a full compliment of existing men plus
    the new workers drafted in that day had to operate was drastically
    reduced. The men themselves had instituted a system of entering by the
    kitchen door and exiting through the garden room door after several
    collisions and hold ups had frustrated tempers and damaged goods. This had
    not solved all of their issues as conflicts over who was doing what and
    where had proliferated. Theodorus recognised that he needed to manage the
    situation by allocating specific jobs to men and making sure that they
    were making due progress, reviewing the whole effort on at least a daily
    basis and adjusting deployments as necessary. He needed Cornelis to
    contribute to the identification of what needed to be done and to apply
    his knowledge of the men's capabilities to their allocation. The two men
    needed to be sure that they didn't contradict each other in directing the
    work yet dividing the overseeing between them to keep things in manageable
    proportions.</para>

    <para>Theodorus was to take charge of the plasterwork and Cornelis the
    woodwork, that much was easy to decide as it played to their specialities.
    How to apportion the painters needed some consideration as both
    plasterwork and woodwork needed painting. However, there was painting and
    then there was painting. Applying base coats of paint required minimal
    skill. Colouring large areas of plain plaster on walls and ceilings
    required enough skill to give an even finish. Similarly smaller but plain
    sections of woodwork, such as doors and skirtings. Then there was carved
    wood and simple plaster mouldings needing care but not the skilled
    brushwork of intricate carvings and mouldings, especially where a steady
    hand and narrow brush were involved. Then there were the special
    techniques involved in imitating marble and different types of wood. These
    later stages of decoration needed carefully arranged drying times to cope
    with the application of different colours and finishes.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>The planned use of rooms in the house during Marcellus's day of
    celebration was to begin with entry by the front door, passing through to
    the vestibule and from thence into the <emphasis>kleine salon</emphasis>
    where refreshments were to be served. When the
    <emphasis>Burgermeester</emphasis> was called to join the celebrations in
    his honour, he and his guests would pass through to the
    <emphasis>gang</emphasis> (making use, if necessary, of the modern toilet
    with its wooden casing wide enough to accommodate the ladies' vast skirts,
    marble walls and flushing bowl), ascend the
    <emphasis>trappenhuis</emphasis> to the <emphasis>witte
    overloop</emphasis> and from there into a small room that led out onto the
    balcony above the front door where Marcellus would stand to view the
    entertainments. Since the balcony itself was quite small, guests could
    also view proceedings from one of the large windows from a narrow gallery
    above the staircase. These areas of the house had to be ready in time and
    completed to the highest possible standard to honour Marcellus. Also, the
    <emphasis>burgermeester </emphasis>needed to be sure that his guests were
    sufficiently impressed in order to vindicate his decision to build a new
    house.</para>

    <para>Out of the eyes of all but his closest family (and servants), the
    <emphasis>Burgermeeseter's</emphasis> private chambers led off the
    <emphasis>witte overloop</emphasis> through a frosted glazed door and
    screen, white on one side to match the entrance to Paulina's quarters
    opposite and brown on the other to follow the theme of Marcellus's rooms.
    Beyond this entrance lay a central hall the eponymous <emphasis>bruine
    overloop</emphasis> or brown hall. A door on the left leading towards the
    front of the house gave into Marcellus's bedroom and thence to his
    dressing room and the innovation of a bathroom. It was expected that
    Marcellus would spend at his first night here following his anniversary
    celebrations so these rooms also needed to be prepared to at least as high
    a standard as the areas of the house on general view. This was the most
    challenging part of the whole construction project, especially the bedroom
    where the <emphasis>Burgermeester</emphasis> had given his taste for the
    trappings of position and wealth full rein.</para>

    <para>The imposing grey and red marble fireplace ensemble filled the space
    between floor and ceiling in the centre of the west wall. The ornate
    carvings of the sections above and below the mirror had survived
    relocation without cracks, chips or any more significant damage thanks to
    careful packing in fine cotton gauze, straw and sacking before being
    crated up. The less ornate sections had also been wrapped and crated in
    straw, but this had been a simpler task. The huge mirror with its curved
    shaping top and bottom had been similarly stored with great care, as had
    its delicate wooden mounting frame. Everyone concerned with installing the
    whole ensemble in its new location breathed a sigh of relief when this had
    been safely accomplished. Only one alteration had been required being the
    relatively straightforward job of taking a bit off the bottom of the
    pillars either side of the fire grate which had originally been taller
    and, some said, in better balance with the mirror section.</para>

    <para>Cornelis Straver and his team of craftsmen could then finish
    installing the Mahogany wood paneling which Marcellus had commissioned. He
    had specified that all of the woodwork be in the 18th Century French
    Regency style, which had sent Cornelis scurrying off to France on a visit
    to the grand palaces of Verssailes and Fontainbleau to see for himself the
    sort of thing Marcellus had in mind. The delicate, curving shapes of the
    panels which edged the ceiling, rather than plaster cornicing, were
    something different from the rest of the house and presented Cornelis with
    an enjoyable challenge to his skill. Theodorus might have felt he got off
    lightly as the plasterwork in this chamber consisted of one, large and
    very smooth area on the ceiling and another small oval above the entry
    door. However, he then had the nightmare of finding a artist who was more
    than competent to execute the swirling skies and cavorting angels which
    continued the French theme on these flat areas of plaster. It was
    something of a relief that the plain wall areas inside their rectilinear
    wooden frames were more simply decorated. in plain, dark green with
    delicate, gold leaf tracery borders.</para>

    <para>Not only had Marcellus given himself a stylish bedroom but also the
    luxury of a separate dressing room, the only one in the house. As was the
    bathroom leading from it, equipped with running hot and cold water and a
    zinc bath tub. The hot water had to be pumped up from the well under the
    kitchen terrace and heated in a geyser. The cold water was collected
    rainwater from the roof then held in a reservoir tank in the attic above.
    This arrangement gave sufficient pressure to work the taps and toilet
    flushes. He had done himself proud but not extended his largess to the
    quarters for his daughter and her husband, which were more conventional
    although they could not be describes as spartan by any stretch of the
    imagination. Nor were the meeting room and guest bedroom beyond which were
    accessed through the door off the <emphasis>bruine overloop</emphasis>
    towards the back of the house as luxurious as Marcellus's chambers,
    although he had insisted that the family crests were prominent in the
    decor.</para>

    <para>On a more domestic note, the downstairs <emphasis>huiskamer
    </emphasis>where Marcellus and his family could sit and could take their
    meals once he was in residence, needed to be available for use. Since the
    celebration was to be in late August and some further weeks of fine
    weather were anticipated, the adjacent <emphasis>tuinkamer</emphasis>, or
    garden room, leading through huge, glass doors to a covered terrace and
    riverside garden beyond should be tidied for use by restless guests. By
    the end of their deliberations, Thoedorus and Cornelis had produced a
    daunting schedule of work and were rather down hearted to realise that
    they would not be able to rest on their laurels after the celebrations as
    much would still remain to be done and with the added complication of the
    master being in residence from time to time when not away on business or
    political involvement. Noise and mess would need to be kept to a minimum
    when Marcellus was home.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para/>
  </section>
</chapter>
