<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.1" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>1873-1874</title>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>The man had been covertly watching Van der Boschstraat 12 for
    several days waiting for a chance to catch Johan Jacob alone but the woman
    of the house had shown no inclination to go out. Johan Jacob could be seen
    in his workroom, presumably pouring over his maps upon the hour rather
    than venturing beyond his front door. It was, of course, only a matter of
    time before he answered the call of the ladies available to cater to his
    less cerebral needs. It was a pity that such a sojourn would likely take
    place during the evening which fact meant that the man had to suffer the
    volatile weather of the spring season with only some slight benefit of the
    cover of darkness at later hours. He had to suffer everything from being
    warmed by blinding sunshine to attacked by hail and sleet borne on a the
    winds of a squally. It was a challenge to his pride to maintain his
    reputation for inconspicuousness under such conditions, especially in the
    barrenness of a street of newly built villas. This particular day had
    begun with those wealthy enough to have the choice out for a stroll to
    enjoy the chirruping of the birdies and surging of sap in the flora whilst
    their servants headed along the street with more purpose, either real or
    invented. Although at pains to dress appropriately for the weather and
    change his general appearance frequently, regulars might begin to sense
    something familiar about him and slow movers have the time to take him in.
    A sudden, spring shower late in the afternoon drove everybody indoors -
    and soaked him to the skin! Fresh, dry clothes and novel ways to conceal
    himself had to be brought into play. Fortunately, activities above and
    below stairs relating to the ritual of dinner kept most folk off the
    street and away from the windows.</para>

    <para>Now the weather had cleared up to reveal an almost full moon and
    brilliant with stars. Very nice and all that but the increased
    illumination made remaining invisible difficult yet again added to which
    the temperature was plummeting towards a late frost. His cold, wet feet
    were starting to go numb but stamping some life and warmth back into them
    risked giving himself away to any nosey busybody. His damp clothes were
    steaming dry but taking the heat from his body with them and a drip was
    forming on the end of his nose.</para>

    <para>Ah, but look here! The front door was opening and, yes, the familiar
    figure of his quarry was emerging from it! The man quietly slipped onto
    the pavement behind Johan Jacob and followed him to a distance safely out
    of view from the house before he took a small, round stone from his pocket
    and lobbed it at Johan Jacob's shoulder. Without breaking his stride,
    Johan Jacob walked on then suddenly diverged from his route and stopped in
    the concealing shelter of a low hanging tree. The man walked past, looking
    and listening, before satisfying himself that they were alone and turning
    back to also duck under the dripping willow branches where Johan Jacob was
    waiting expectantly.</para>

    <para>"You will be taking ship for Sumatra and must report for briefing at
    1600 the day after tomorrow. Go in uniform but take informal tropical
    clothing. We will sort you out some better gear when you get there. So,
    travel light and with concealed small arms . You'll be away months rather
    than weeks. Questions? "</para>

    <para>Johan Jacob stared thoughtfully at his shoes then nodded his head to
    accept the brief before adding,</para>

    <para>"Then I had better make haste and take full use of the delights at
    my destination."</para>

    <para>With that, he turned on his heel and strode off into the
    night.</para>

    <para>The man waited until the footsteps had died away before peering
    through the drooping willow branches to ensure that the coast was He
    quietly took himself off in the direction of the less salubrious parts of
    Den Haag where he would not attract attention in a smoke-filled bar which
    specialised in cheap <emphasis>jenever</emphasis>. The result of his
    efforts to reheat through the ingestion of rough spirit was that pretty
    much all of him not just his extremities, was pleasantly anaesthetized by
    the time he set out for the docks at Scheveningen. He had also contrived
    to spill most of his last <emphasis>shot jenever</emphasis> down his
    front, which was a waste! Luckily the novel form of the ironclad monitor
    vessel he was to rendezvous with was easily spotted amongst the wooden
    sailing ships and steam-sailers in port. The
    <emphasis>Heiligerlee</emphasis> was a common sight along the coast of
    Holland so attracted no longer attracted any undue interest by arriving in
    Schveningen.</para>

    <para>The man merged himself with a group of sailors whose direction of
    travel indicated that they were headed in the way he wanted to go. They
    had clearly been ashore for a drink but were not inebriated since this
    would result on being put on a charge as soon as they returned to the
    ship. He joined them in the companionable activity of relieving themselves
    into the dock from the edge of the quay. As he turned inshore, having
    concluded his business, he staggered and went to make a step backwards
    which would have likely precipitated him into the water below. A large,
    calloused hand grasped him firmly under the arms and set him back on the
    right track.</para>

    <para>"Steady as you go, Matey! You'll be for it when the officer on deck
    sees the state you're in!"</para>

    <para>His saviour accompanied him to the foot of the gangway to ensure his
    safety before leaving him to make his slow and unsteady way to the deck at
    the top.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis>Adelborst</emphasis> (or Sergeant) on duty was marking
    off the returning crew to make sure no one was missing but stuck his arm
    out when the man reached him thus preventing his further passage onto the
    deck. He had been watching the group of sailors as they drained their
    bilges and had seen this one experiencing heavy weather, rolling
    noticeably and being blown off course from time to time so requiring the
    services of a tug boat in the burley shape of the chief stoker. He reeked
    of alcohol and, when asked his name and rank, was unable to articulate
    more than a slurred mumble. Heaving a sigh of resignation, the
    <emphasis>Adelborst</emphasis> snapped his fingers towards the Master at
    Arms waiting nearby and instructed him to convey the miscreant to the brig
    to sober up and await being brought before the Commander on a
    charge.</para>

    <para>The <emphasis>Heiligerlee</emphasis> had been built with a shallow
    draft of just under 3m, armor plated sides, a low freeboard and armed with
    a few but heavy guns. She was designed to patrol the coast and rivers in
    case of invasion in the aftermath of the Franco-Prussian War. A sturdy and
    useful vessel, she was also the butt of humour because of some rather
    unfortunate '<emphasis>incidents</emphasis>', running aground between
    Dordrecht and Rotterdam then again in the opposite direction, following
    this up by hitting a bridge on the same route.</para>

    <para>Since the<emphasis> Heiligerlee </emphasis>was only in Scheveningen
    harbour for a few hours, most of her complement of 117 men had stayed on
    board so had not had opportunity to get into trouble, hence the man had
    the brig to himself. A guard had been rustled up to keep and eye on him in
    case he hurt himself or choked on his won vomit, but mostly retreat to a
    discrete hideout where he could smoke, read the racing papers and doze
    noisily. His deception having achieved its objective, the man wrapped
    himself in the single, rough, navy blanket and lay down on the bunk,
    promptly falling into a sound sleep. He was woken by a different guard
    bringing in a tray of breakfast and suggesting that he visit the heads and
    clean himself up before being brought before Luitenant 1e klas W F Meijen.
    The man availed himself of both breakfast and bathroom facilities,
    returning to the brig to find a pile of clean clothes on the bunk.</para>

    <para>The commander dismissed the guard who had escorted the man and
    closed his cabin door behind. The two men could now talk in
    private.</para>

    <para>"I was beginning to think that you had missed our rendezvous and I
    had had to leave without you. Then a sheepish crewman reported that he
    thought there was a stowaway as he had a supernumerary on his return from
    shore leave list. We have only just left winter quarters in Rotterdam and
    have had a change of about half of the crew since last year so the new
    names and faces are not familiar yet. Hence you had managed to slip past
    him, much to his embarrassment. He sought to redeem himself by having
    thrown you in the brig where I trust you had a restful night."</para>

    <para>The man reassured him that the hotel service on his ship was of an
    acceptable standard!</para>

    <para>"The crewman I sent to you this morning can be trusted to be
    discrete and the chap from last night is too ashamed of himself to spread
    rumours so your stay with us will be as <emphasis>sub Rosa </emphasis>as
    it can be. We are patrolling the coast as normal as we head towards Den
    Helder where we are to drop you off. Currently we are at IJ-Muiden to make
    sure there is nothing untoward happening.</para>

    <para>The heavy excavation work on construction of the North Sea Canal has
    brought in navvies from Germany and Belgium as well as home grown
    polderlabourers. There are even some English working on the locks, but
    they tend to keep to themselves. Liquor is a problem among the single men
    in the barracks. The families in their makeshift hut and holes in the
    ground are scattered among the sand dunes among the dunes are more of a
    cause for concern as we have practically no control over them and
    infiltration would be a simple matter for German interests. The practice
    of hiring part of the workforce on a daily basis means that strangers can
    come and go practically unnoticed. On top of this there are a lot of
    fishing boats coming off the North Sea for shelter in the estuary and some
    come to trade their catches. Who knows what agents might be coming and
    going by this sea route.</para>

    <para>Not wishing to add to our unfortunate reputation, we have to be wary
    of the sand which accumulates in the harbour despite regular dredging. All
    we can do is send a couple of tenders ashore for a look round and maintain
    a discouraging presence. Assuming we don't encounter any problems, we
    should be on our way north within the hour and dock in Willemsoord at
    around half twelve. You are welcome to use my cabin until then. Is there
    anything you need?"</para>

    <para>The man only had a request for more coffee and maybe a stroopwaffel
    for his sweet tooth.</para>

    <para>As the commander made to leave to take his place on the bridge, he
    turned back with a slight twist to his smile;</para>

    <para>"We are about to set the sails to save eating into our reserves of
    coal and water to run the engine. She doesn't sail well and we have a beam
    sea most of the way so you may end up wishing that we had made one of our
    unscheduled stops!"</para>

    <para>With that he shut the cabin door behind him leaving the man to
    contemplate how long he would hang on to his breakfast.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Johan Jacob joined three other uniformed men in a small meeting room
    at the Willemsoord naval base. All were in uniform but only one other was
    a naval officer. A rather fearsome looking <emphasis>Seargeant</emphasis>
    from the <emphasis>Korps Mariniers </emphasis>(or Marines) and a small,
    wiry chap wearing the unadorned naval uniform of a <emphasis>Marinier 3e
    Klasse</emphasis> made up the quartet. They were all strangers to one
    another so sat in silence trying to surreptitiously eye each other up. If
    they were nonplussed so far, they were awestruck when they realized that
    the man who now strode into the room sported the
    <emphasis>Schout-bij-nacht </emphasis>(or Rear Admiral) uniform. He had a
    bundle of official-looking document files under one arm and stamped his
    authority on the briefing by stationing himself behind the lectern at the
    front of the room.</para>

    <para>After a suitable interval to let the room settle and focus attention
    on him, he began;</para>

    <para>"Gentlemen. Your country has need of your services on an
    intelligence mission. You will undoubtedly have read in the newspapers or
    heard by word of mouth about the campaign to conquer the
    <emphasis>Sultanaat</emphasis> <emphasis>Atjeh</emphasis> (or Sutanate of
    Aceh) on the northern tip of Sumatra in the <emphasis>Oost
    Indische</emphasis> (or East Indies). The purpose of the action was to
    consolidate Dutch control over the whole of the island in the light of a
    threat from foreign interests in <emphasis>Atjeh</emphasis>. What is known
    only to a select group, of which you will now become members, is that this
    expedition went even more disastrously wrong than is public
    knwoledge."</para>

    <para>Another pause whilst his audience registered their dismay then
    settled again.</para>

    <para>"Catastrophic mistakes were made for which the commanding officer,
    <emphasis>generaal-majoor</emphasis> Kohler, and eighty of his men paid
    with their lives. <emphasis>Atjeh</emphasis> is of enormous importance to
    our <emphasis>koloniale politik </emphasis><emphasis>van</emphasis>
    <emphasis>uitbreiding</emphasis> (or policy of colonial expansion) as it
    represents the last area of Sumatra which remains independent of Dutch
    control. It derives much of its wealth from the growth of pepper and, less
    acceptably, from piracy along its busy coastline. The recent discovery of
    oil fields promises to be of major significance in the future and we need
    these to be a Dutch resource. Incorporating <emphasis>Atjeh</emphasis>
    into Sumtra, with its proximity to Java, is an objective which must be
    attained.</para>

    <para>Gentlemen, your remit is to ensure that a second expedition does not
    fail. The folders which I am passing out now contain descriptions of the
    action during the first expedition and such analysis of its failure as has
    been made so far. Familiarise yourselves with this material. Subject the
    analysis to scrutiny and be ready to advance the understandings it offers.
    Once we set sail for <emphasis>Atjeh</emphasis> I will furnish you with an
    account of the strategy for the second expedition which is under the
    strictest of security protocols. You will then be in a position to
    identify vital intelligence requirements and to formulate plans for
    gathering the necessary information yourselves.</para>

    <para>You will have plenty of time to complete this phase of your
    operation on the voyage out to <emphasis>Atjeh</emphasis>, some 8,00
    nautical miles even with the shortcut through the Suez Canal. You will
    take ship on the <emphasis>Banda</emphasis> , a newly commissioned
    <emphasis>Riouw</emphasis> class gunship. You have each been selected for
    your different specialist skills so need to get to know each other and
    form effective working relationships. You will also receive input on the
    local languages and customs as well as training on covert operations and
    self defence. I'm afraid that you might also be required to cover for crew
    absences as the <emphasis>Banda</emphasis> does not have space to
    accommodate passengers.</para>

    <para>The Commander of the <emphasis>Banda</emphasis> is expecting you at
    1700 for drinks before a formal welcome dinner. He expects to depart on
    the first tide tomorrow. I bid you safe voyage, good luck and God
    speed."</para>

    <para>With that he strode from the room.</para>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para/>

    <para/>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para/>
  </section>
</chapter>
